[Music]
thank you
hello everyone welcome this is active
live stream number 49.0
we're discussing the paper a worked
example of the Bayesian mechanics of
classical objects
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to activeinference.org to
learn more about participating in
different projects and learning groups
at The Institute
well
we're here today in live stream number
49.0 where we're providing some
background in context for the paper a
worked example of the Bayesian mechanics
of classical objects
this paper was submitted to the archive
preprint server in June 2022 and we're
going to be discussing and looking at a
slightly revised version that was
uploaded earlier this month on the 6th
of September it's a single author paper
by Dalton a r sakh diva devel
and this video
um although all dot zeros are this one
is two it's an introduction and just a
preliminary discussion of some of the
ideas it's not a review or a synthesis
or a final word
and we'll explain a little bit more
about our DOT zero approach in a couple
of slides but suffice to say that with
Jacob Ali and also under we had a great
time over the last two months really
pulling back and trying to think deeply
about how to frame this paper and really
this whole area of research and
development because there's a lot
happening there's a lot being tied
together and so we hope that some of
that sense making translates into the
ways that we've laid out 49.0
and we're very much looking forward to
having Dalton join for the dot one and
the dot two so Dalton thanks for all the
work and for listening to this dot zero
let's head to introductions and warm-ups
so we can just say hello and any other
features of what we're excited about in
this discussion I'm Daniel I'm a
researcher in California and
I think there's a lot that is exciting
about this paper I didn't have much of a
physics background before heading
towards
active inference in the free energy
principle so taking a first look
at a lot of these physics ideas
was interesting like seeing them as part
of something that already could or had
been integrated rather than starting
with the puzzle pieces I think was a
little bit interesting
and I'll pass to Ali
hi
I'm Ali I'm an independent researcher
from Iran
actually what gravitated me towards
active inference paper this I mean fep
were active in Prince literature and
particularly this paper was
uh you see I was always uh
I've been fascinated by uh doing uh the
the kind of elegant abstractions and uh
and some physical Concepts or some uh
doing uh a kind of bird's-eyed view over
uh the the methodological way of doing
uh physical modeling and uh I believe
this paper and the other related papers
uh offered by uh Dalton secretable and
the other and his other colleagues from
versus lab uh are the epitome of uh this
kind of uh fep abstraction in terms of
uh elegantly formalizing all the
rigorous mathematical foundations of it
and uh yeah that's why I'm pretty
excited to be here actually it's been a
very fascinating and thrilling Journey
during the past couple of months since
we began
discussing this paper and so I'm very
much looking forward to it
foreign
I'm a student and researcher in the UK
um there are also many uh
okay lost Jacob for a second
we'll just wait we'll take a breath
okay
it's all good
oh where was I cut off just start at the
beginning
maybe turn off your video
okay
c'est la vie
your backyard cup just start at the
beginning it's all good
okay uh sorry I got randomly
disconnected uh so hello I'm jakub I'm a
student uh and researcher in the UK uh
I'm really I was really excited about
this paper specifically coming from uh
physics background which I must say
didn't help that much in initially
understanding the paper on the on the
first pass uh but I think it's really
exciting
um that this kind of unification of
physics and cognitive Sciences uh is
formed through uh works like uh this
paper or prior work
um that Carl friston colleagues have
been working on
and I am really excited about how this
work might
um influence the future Synergy of
physics and
cognitive Sciences or neurosciences
which
uh I think previously were quite
disjoint Fields but now uh with the uh
more Focus towards like complexity
scientists were seeing these uh
similar patterns across a wide range of
topics which I find really exciting so
really looking forward to
the discussion and
the rest of the live stream
great
great thanks so we're going to go to the
big question Ames claims abstract and
roadmap
and then before we head off on that road
trip and we find together we're going to
pull back to our approach and set a lot
of context and that'll be most of this
dot zero video and then we'll briefly
touch on some points from the paper but
most of this video is going to be
actually in that context setting
there's a lot of big questions that can
be asked and one of them is quite simply
what is Bayesian mechanics
but to make that a little bit more
operational we could ask what is the
relevance of Bayesian mechanics
what is mechanical about cognitive
science are we talking about physical
mechanisms underlying cognitive agents
or are we talking about something else
it's the second
what is of epistemic
and pragmatic value about Bayesian
mechanics if we're going to be using
active inference in the free energy
Principle as the gripper and the gripped
then how can we understand what is
valuable and relevant in salience in
terms of active inference ways of
thinking about it
what would you fellows add what felt
like really big questions that would
lead somebody to want to be exploring
this paper
yeah Ali
well actually uh before talking about
the specific pragmatic value of doing
Bayesian mechanics I think what at least
in my view what's really interesting
about uh basically a mechanical way of
doing these kind of uh probabilistic
formulations and mathematical
modeling is just it's pure Elegance in
okay
pick up again from Pure different
elements I mean
sorry Ali pick up from Pure Elegance
okay uh yeah as I was saying uh I think
uh one of its main interests is its pure
Elegance in unifying uh the different
approaches to fep in a kind of uh
all-encompassing uh framework called am
Bayesian mechanics by which uh it can
possibly uh I mean the other uh
Frameworks and other viewpoints and even
other kinds of mechanics can be
recovered so uh at least for me
personally this is the most interesting
part and exciting part of uh doing
Bayesian mechanics but I'm sure there
will be much pragmatic value and much
more applications
that can potentially derive from the
this kind of viewpoint
awesome where's Beauty and elegance in
epistem and pragma Jakob
um I definitely agree with with Ali's
point and maybe to add to that I think
it's really elegant that within Bayesian
mechanics you have a unifying formalism
with which you can recover
much of the same loss that we see in
classical physics
um also we can also uh
talk about the quantum mechanics as
being
um
enclosed within the Bayesian mechanic
formalism but at the same time using the
same uh
those same Concepts we can also model
systems which are not usually considered
by physics like uh
autonomous agents or but any biological
entity and
that I think will be one of the probably
one of the most relevant
parts or contributions of of Bayesian
mechanics
awesome
Beauty as
um and in Elegance as uh indicators of
scope and scale
so the paper is a worked example of the
Bayesian mechanics of classical objects
we've mentioned some details about it
before
I'll just highlight
um a few claims some coming earlier
in the middle and later in the paper
so earlier in the paper
it's written it's often claimed that the
free energy principle is as simple in
general as the principle of stationary
action and that is a citation to a paper
that we're going to discuss in just a
few slides simpler but not too simple
and it's claimed about the fep that it
can be sketched out how Bayesian
mechanics of internal states of
classical objects might look and that's
a citation to friston 2019 free energy
principle for a particular physics which
we're also going to look at
nevertheless there's yet to be a
systematic investigation of even the
Bayesian mechanics of classical physics
despite it being readily available due
to recent formulations as a leased
action principle so we've talked a lot
about on these streams and elsewhere
about the free energy Principle as a
variational principle of least action
for cognitive systems
so there was an opportunity that Dalton
identified which is to make a systematic
investigation of classical physics and
provide worked examples
towards the middle of the paper there
are some important aims such as we began
with the aim of showing that classical
physics can be derived from Bayesian
mechanics so we'll work with different
metaphors and ways of exploring it but
this is not like a layer two on physics
this is a generalization that in special
cases includes classical statistical
thermodynamic and quantum mechanics
we can derive Bayesian mechanics from
the idea that a system is classical on
average just as we can derive classical
mechanics from the idea that systems
obey Bay Bayesian Mechanics for
classical averages
we're going to unpack that later but
it's a key claim and then later in the
paper there is the aim to eventually
formulate chaotic or itinerant systems
under Bayesian mechanics as has been
done for earlier forms of the free
energy principle and that's kind of what
the paper is going to be leading towards
and suggesting for future work including
that of G Theory
anything that you fellows would add
all right
um could somebody read the abstract
uh yeah but before going to into
abstract I wanted to point out uh one of
the main goals of the paper I think uh
would be uh
there are a couple of new results
in this paper that uh wasn't introduced
as far as I know in the previous uh
literature one of which is uh the
derivation of classical physics from the
principle of constraint maximum entropy
and the reintroduction of supersymmetry
as an explanation for uh classical chaos
as indicated on page five of the paper
uh so I think this is in some way uh
this paper is a kind of expanded
footnote to the previous papers but also
adding some new results uh I mean it's
very important
appendix to that paper by making uh some
of the theoretical claims of
specifically on Bayesian mechanics paper
more concrete
so yeah I just wanted to point that out
as well great great point this should be
of interest to people who are following
the development and applications of
active inference and free energy
principle but it will become clear that
the scope is very Broad and people even
outside of what might be perceived as
just this community will hopefully find
interest and apply scrutiny and continue
the conversation with us so somebody May
read the abstract
sure uh so Bayesian mechanics is a new
approach to studying the mathematics and
physics of interacting stochastic
processes here we provide a worked
example of a physical Mechanics for
classical objects which derives from a
simple application thereof we summarize
the current state of the art of Bayesian
mechanics in doing so we also give a
sketch of its connections to classical
chaos owing to a particular n equals to
supersymmetry
short and sweet
to the roadmap
all right so the paper begins with uh
I'm putting us our video over the the
top fellow on this uh stack
so the paper begins with an introduction
and then dives into the concept of
mechanics which we'll be talking more
about the subsections there are covering
classical physics in one dimension the
basics of Bayesian mechanics a physics
of beliefs and then a physics by beliefs
which is going to be kind of taking us
into this cognitive lens
then a general equation equation 15 or
Bayesian classical mechanics is
presented and that'll be a really
exciting equation in formalism to lead
up to and unpack
the following section 4 is a question of
quantum ontology this is going to touch
on discussions that we've had including
in live stream 40 on the free energy
principle for generic Quantum systems
and about what Quantum means and how we
can think about things that are often
described as being at the atomic scale
whether it's the idea of quantum
mechanics itself or bosons and fermions
and all these other kind of like weight
but I thought that was at the atom scale
and what does it mean to apply it to
cognitive systems
there's then several cases that are
addressed and those are the worked
examples that's the matching of modes
the tracking of modes with the
subdivision into terminal mode matching
and infinite mode tracking and then
towards the end there's the adventuring
into path tracking these are the three
phases of Bayesian mechanics mode
matching mode tracking and path tracking
we're going to look into it and a simple
case of G Theory and so that is where
one gets to by the end of this journey
but before we head off as promised we're
going to dwell for a second on how we
can set context to even head off on this
journey so would anyone like to just
describe like what the sections that
we're about to jump into are about
and what led us to use this approach
uh oh yes uh actually
as we discussed before
um we will Begin by looking at some
historical perspectives and historical
contexts of all the developments of FAP
literature throughout the past two
decades and then we'll look at some of
the key literature uh on which this
particular paper relies upon and then
we'll look at some the three kinds of
theories
uh
that's been introduced in uh on Bayesian
mechanics paper as
uh the way of anchoring all the
theoretical uh arguments there and uh
finally we'll talk about uh the three
non-bayesian mechanics before delving
into what Bayesian mechanics uh is and
what are the differences and
similarities between uh all the
different kinds of doing uh the physics
or mechanics
awesome this we hope sets the discussion
within a historical and uh
integrationist framing
and it's going to be
quite a journey so let's head into this
section
first let's talk about some historical
perspectives and different epochs of
research
broadly we can think about what happened
before the free energy principles
emergence in the pre-2000 the
pre-millennial era without going too
specifically into the
um what citation the free energy
principle originates in
then we can think about the free energy
principle between roughly 2005
all the way up through 2020 around
and then lastly
some of the changes and developments in
free energy principle literature since
about 2019 to 20 and some of Dalton's
contributions
so starting with the free energy
principle before 2000.
there's no definitive history yet for
the antecedents of the free energy
principle and surely a presentation or
project more focused on that history
could and should and will happen
but a few of the places to search for in
terms of the personal history of key
contributors and also places where uh
peripheral contributions and important
foundational precursors are described
some places to look include the
statistical parametric mapping textbook
and documentation and the Decades of
research that went into the neuroimaging
work on SPM
as well as a Carl friston 2012 article
the history of the future of the
Bayesian brain
and an interview with Carl friston on
wood lice and Men
as well as the uh auxiliary supplement
to the above interview am I autistic and
intellectual autobiography so that'll
take somebody from the sort of zero to
eight
and then 8 to 28 and then 28 and Beyond
of Carl friston's work and development
with copious references out
on the right is a slide from live stream
14 where we explore just one aspect of
tracing the thread which was from the
analytical formalizations of for example
Markov in terms of statistics and
matrices
all the way on through Pearl and the
computational implementation of Bayesian
statistics
On Through To modern developments that
integrate those kinds of Bayesian
formulations of Statistics with action
which encompasses a variety of fields
such as cybernetics complex systems
synergetics information Theory control
theory ecological psychology for
e-cognition extended embodied etc etc
autonomous systems and all other types
of Frameworks so
it would be a history of the world to
talk about everything that happened
before 2000 but these are just some
threats anything else that people want
to add
yeah maybe
um that as the as the theory gets more
integrated to various different fields I
think it's going to be
harder and harder to actually find that
one thread that was the the development
towards the free energy principle where
the reality is probably that
uh as with all roads leading to Rome
many
trajectories lead
to the free energy principle
nice
Ollie
uh and also related
to this historical context I wanted to
point out the uh the heated discussions
that's going on uh during the last
couple of years about the use of uh I
mean some established vocabulary or
terminology inactive inference or fep
literature one of which is using the
markup blanket in a kind of different
context but as
a Maxwell ramstead's uh Twitter Fred
from yesterday as pointed out to a very
interesting example we can say
we can say the same for a lot of
mathematical constructs for example we
can look at the concept of zero as a
purely mathematical construct but used
in different contexts for example it can
be used as a null as a null container or
a null
counter but on the other hand it can be
seen as the solution of the polynomial
or a function and the same goes here for
using the the same mathematical
construct or theoretical construct of
Markov blanket but in a different
context but that doesn't mean markup
blankets or anytime any other
theoretical
Concepts used in FTP literature
are denying the or somehow are
contradictory with the previous uh usage
of that terminology it's just used in uh
different contexts
awesome
so as a really concise way to summarize
again something where further
presentations and work can do a much
more comprehensive job there's a Maxwell
ramstad tweet thread from 7-Eleven 2020.
and Maxwell breaks down developments in
the free energy principle modeling into
several waves and the Tweet thread is
readable here the first wave doesn't
have policy selection per se the
Dynamics of internal and active States
was determined in a stepwise fashion
through gradient descent on variational
free energy and so that was very much
like a pure one-step gradient descent
framework
second wave models started around 2012
equipped agents with beliefs about State
Transitions and the sensory consequences
of movement
that allows the calculation of expected
free energy like
values and third wave models use a
recursive expected free energy
functional which opens up all of these
uh related Avenues so Maxwell's thread
here
summarizes some of the waves of
development
and there's so much more to add and
unpack because there's been developments
on multiple different fronts or I
wouldn't even know what word to say
there has been formal developments
and Technical elaborations
as well as generalizations
and
also of course a huge area of
philosophical discussion around these
topics so
um there's been a lot happening since
2005 to 2020 in free energy principle
and
this is going to get us up to where
we're ready to explore what's happened
in the last few years from this kind of
building momentum and
uh
progress in the space anything to add
Jacob
um
um maybe just
a short comment that
I think a lot uh a lot of the first and
perhaps even the second wave uh we can
probably see more influence of
um
Carl's Preston's prior work on SPM
um and all the literature that uh
surrounds it whereas in the kind of
third age or third wave uh we are seeing
more Integrations into other fields like
um physics and
oh welcome complexity science
great Point as the literature builds and
as other collaborators began to upskill
and contribute then we start seeing some
different approaches but there's
initially a lot of similarities with SPM
and it's really still quite a useful
framework to use of course but also
point back towards
all right then on to the third epoch
that's post 2020 and Dalton's
contributions so we
laughed and had a great time
reviewing many of the fascinating
developments over the last few years
in a range of topics made by Dalton
ranging from fundamental physics to
neuroscience and most recently Bayesian
mechanics and G Theory a lot of the work
is single author other papers and works
of note are collaborations for example
with ramstead friston and others and
this is just a few this is some subset
screenshots from our coda
knowledge integration work where we have
a bunch of papers blog posts videos
tweets we were just bringing together a
lot of different information and we'll
look forward to hearing it from The
Source soon enough
the specific papers that we want to
discuss we're going to in the next
session but this is all to say that it's
been a quite productive streak for
Dalton and an awesome learning
experience for us all so we really
appreciate all that work and we're
looking forward to the conversations
anything you want to add on this outside
of the literature
all right
next we will go to the literature we're
going to go through about four or five
papers
that are important steps on the way to
getting to the worked example
so let's just go right into it
this is going to be a paper from outside
of the friston sphere
in in one sense but not in another sense
it's a 2012 paper by Udo Seifert
and the paper is called stochastic
thermodynamics fluctuation theorems and
molecular machines
surely the paper is worth a deeper take
but just to highlight at the very high
level
stochastic thermodynamics as reviewed
here systematically provides a framework
for extending the notion of classical
thermodynamics such as work heat and
entropy production to the level of
individual trajectories of well-defined
non-equilibrium ensembles
that is going to be a key move and theme
which is a move from a um kind of
undifferentiated mass action or mean
field approximation physics
and finding compatibility between that
kind of an averaging
and recovering that averaging outcome
via
individual trajectories of well-defined
non-equilibrium ensembles
one can imagine that if they're
interested in the consideration of
specific counterfactual policies or in
the behavior of multi-agent ensembles
Simply Having a mean field approximation
the kind of which classical
thermodynamics has provided for work key
in entropy production
it'll be another step and potentially an
unprincipled or intractable one to ever
go from that mean field down to the
trajectory level and so the kind of
synthesis work that has to occur and is
pointed towards here is to understand
how a special case or abridging
formalism can connect this kind of mean
field population scale summary statistic
aggregate worlds two
individual trajectories of well-defined
non-equilibrium ensembles
anything else to add on this paper
uh well actually I think
uh one of its I mean the central
importance of this paper to uh exactly
vandeville's current paper is the the
definition of uh the probability the
past probability measure in the abstract
wiener space uh mainly the equation
number five which I believe is a very
significant preliminary stage toward
deriving the general equation of
Bayesian mechanics or equation 15.
excellent on to the next paper
the next paper is a single author paper
by Carl friston in 2019
a free energy principle for a particular
physics so it's a little small on the
slide but this is like an 148 page paper
and you'll note there on the header this
work is under consideration for
publication by the MIT press so there's
an interesting story
who's middle and end is unknown about
the recent active inference textbook and
the way in which that is providing kind
of a handbook of active inference but
then there's something more like a
theoretical physics book that is going
to be presented in some future time
particular physics is a
multi entender or a pun in a few
different ways this is a particular
physics in the sense that because it's
being specified it's like a specified or
a specific physics like any dinner that
you make is a particular dinner in that
sense
also really key
to this notion of individual
trajectories of well-defined
non-equilibrium ensembles is the notion
of the particle and the particular
States the particular states are
referring to when we have a partition
that uses the Markov blanket so blanket
States making internal and external
States conditionally independent we can
then talk about the blanket and the
internal States as the particular States
because they're like the particle that's
floating around so in the Brownian
mechanics world then you have the dust
molecule floating around in the water
and the particle is the dust molecule
and then the external states are the
water and along those lines the
cognitive particle is going to be the
internal and the blanket States that's
what's going to have cognitive mass and
inherit all of these physics terms that
might be kind of like billiard balls are
to classical mechanics we're going to be
looking at what that particulate form is
for cognitive systems
this was an extremely important work
conceptually as well as
uh socially Maxwell ramstead facilitated
and organized a really amazing
Discussion Group over many months
working with a lot of people to go
through chapters and surfacing a lot of
important thoughts that could be
connected technical contributions raised
by many participants in that reading
group and um
the work itself
is a theory of everything
but perhaps in a way that people might
not expect so I'll just pause there if
either of you want to give any overview
thoughts on the monograph what does it
mean by a theory of everything or what
else would you add about this precursor
paper
in fact I wanted to point out uh
an important note uh stated in the
footnote number one of uh the classical
physics paper
and
is T in this paper by Carl friston
the word particle is used as you
mentioned
for the combination or the joint set of
internal and blank States
but in the current paper Dalton prefers
to use the word system for that concept
and
where in for instance paper refers to
system Dalton's paper uses
um agent environmentally so that might
be helpful for people who want to read
that read the literature because in the
rest of the literature it's basically
the same thing the word particle is used
as the joint set of the internal and
blanket States but not in this one
thank you Jacob want to add anything on
the paper
um maybe just do slightly uh add on The
Theory of Everything uh that refers to
the notion that anything that exists
needs to have some kind of statistical
independence from its environment
um which is uh which constitutes a
Markov blanket and I think we'll see in
the in the coming slides that uh some
contributions from Dalton have also
shown this to be the case
in uh in cases where
the fep has previously been criticized
uh for not actually applying generally
to
um
to systems which uh don't reach that
threshold
um
so yeah just wanted to uh add that
nice when people talk about a theory of
everything and they leave out the space
they might mean like a theory of all of
it
but this is actually a theory of all of
the open parentheses Observer dependent
modeler dependent close parenthesis
things that can be distinguished again
that's where the Observer is in the
distinguishing
from other things in a statistical sense
if you can't distinguish it over the
time scale of observation it's just not
a thing
it's not to say that it's not part of
someone else's theory of all of it but
in this sense it's not a thing and
that's what is also setting up at a very
fundamental level for this notion of
systems engaging in the bounding of
surprise
because systems that don't bound
will not be observed to be that kind of
thing in the way that the surprise was
limiting
and the work also points importantly
towards compatibility among Quantum
statistical and classical mechanics
those are the three non-bayesian
mechanics that we're going to be going
into Bayesian mechanics is going to
generalize and Encompass and integrate
across all of these
and
it may offer a formal description of
lifelike particles
for example classical mechanics could
tell you what happens when a 200 pound
object falls out of a plane but I think
as Dean has raised what happens when
that entity has a parachute so there's
something different there and what could
the reductionist physicist do other than
try to make a physics model of the elbow
and of the ions coming in and out of the
neurons reductionism is kind of the way
in that situation and so we're going to
be talking about potentially a way to
see that active particle falling out of
the plane as something that could engage
in agentic decisions
next paper
this next paper is the free energy
principle made simpler but not too
simple
be careful
um it is a paper from
Carl friston DeCosta Sajid Heinz
alzhoffer poliotis and Par we discussed
this paper in several discussions
earlier this year in live stream number
45. we have 45.0 background in context
and we have the dot 1 and the dot two
with uh Thomas Parr and Carl first and
joining for the discussion and say many
interesting and funny things
the paper is providing a concise
description of the free energy principle
which begins from a Lang Van equation
and ends with a Bayesian mechanics that
can be read as a physics of sentience
noting here that sentience refers to
feeling and acting entities not to
qualia phenomenology experiential
entities per se although people have
provided interpretations that go that
way
this paper rehearses key steps using
standard results from statistical
physics
those steps are going to be one
establish a particular partition of
States based upon conditional
independencies inheriting from sparse
coupling again particular is being used
in the pun since as it was before this
is like one specific partition that you
could choose to implement and it's the
one that results in particles
two unpacking the implications of that
particular partition in terms of
Bayesian inference
one of the kinds of inference that's
really important is about internal
States doing inference on external
States mediated through sense states on
the blanket and then three describing
the paths of particular states with a
variational principle of least action
which is going to tie us towards
understanding individual trajectories of
well-defined non-equilibrium ensembles
um
this paper
was a
discussed elsewhere so here's Brock and
I in the dot zero talking about
non-equilibrium birds and then here
um we have blue and Carl and Thomas and
we're just trying to catch up with what
they're adding
anything that you fellows would add
about this paper
all right now we're going to enter into
the Dalton Zone
so
this is in April 2022.
Dalton presents a single author paper
towards a geometry and Analysis for
Bayesian mechanics
the paper presents a simple case of
Bayesian mechanics under the free energy
principle and formulates it
axiomatically
there's going to be a lot of interesting
things to unpack
um
does anyone want to just give their read
on the importance of this paper
uh I think uh this is one of the first
papers uh Dalton has attempted to
provide the rigorous mathematical
foundation for fep uh by providing uh
some formal proofs of the relevant
theorems but without uh I mean going
into
a lot of technical jargons I mean this
paper is a pretty accessible uh for
people even
not specialized in mathematical proofs
and so on but I mean by skipping those
technical mathematical proofs the whole
conceptual framework or the gist of the
paper is totally accessible in my
opinion so I think this is one of uh the
very significant and important steps
toward developing uh the more
comprehensive Theory provided in the
neck in their next paper on Bayesian
mechanics
great
this is uh going to be connecting the
random dynamical systems formalization
and takes a further step towards
comprehensive statement of the physics
of self-organization in formal
mathematical language
which is presented using gauge Theory
and some geometric Notions and that's
going to create a concordance that can
be at least
stated qualitatively but has a lot of
technical underpinnings which is the
relationship between the dynamical
systems notion of self-organization in
terms of bounded surprise
connecting that to
a gauge theoretic formalism of
self-organization in which gauge forces
are acting on the system
and others can and please should help us
unpack this and do math streams with us
and do a DOT three four five
here we're going to point a little bit
more briefly to two recent papers uh
well they're all recent it's only
September 2022. this was only five
months ago
here is a paper from uh August actually
both of them are from August but the
first one was first published in July
the first paper is weak Markov blankets
in high dimensional sparsely coupled
random dynamical systems that's a paper
by Dalton and then a paper with Maxwell
Dalton and Carl on the map territory
fallacy fallacy would either of you like
to just pick one of them and just
describe like what was cool or important
about these papers
I would uh maybe say on the weak Mark of
blankets in high dimensional as
partially a couple of random dynamical
systems I think that paper is really
crucial because it
does unpack a lot of
um a lot of uncertainty that
many people might have uh had with the
fep before
uh especially the spark sparse coupling
conjecture uh that finally received a
formal formal proof
um
and I think it's also
important in
this paper that we are uh going to going
to discuss especially when we are
talking about systems at the quantum
scale or beyond beyond the quantum scale
where
sparse coupling is more uh
is a much
more present notion than non-sparce
coupling
um
yeah I think this is
a key paper uh in
all of these uh prerequisite papers
thank you Ali feel free to say something
you like about either or both
uh adding to
what Jacob said about weak marker
Blanket's paper I think uh one other uh
significant contribution of this paper
to the fep literature is the
introduction of the concept of blanket
index which was a very I mean sorely
needed concept uh because uh I mean by
uh grading the markup blankets by by
this concept uh we we can see that
when we talk and talk about any markup
blankets it's not a singular or I don't
know necessarily uh 100 consistent
concept but it can be graded
um
according to this blanket index namely
that when the blanket index is zero we
have the strongest markup blanket uh I
mean that also recovers the sparse
um coupled conjecture but when it
maximizes we have this concept of me
weak markup blankets which is uh
basically what uh most linear systems
has most linear systems have
but when we
discuss the higher dimensional systems
or more complex systems uh the markup
the blanket index uh somehow minimizes
or in fact uh goes to zero in sparse
coupled
systems
awesome Yes it
is an important contribution and maybe
we can unpack this paper more as they're
also become more perhaps worked examples
of weekly mixing Markov blanket the
zones
and anything to add on map territory
fallacy fallacy
go further
and yeah this is also a kind of uh I
believe a response to some of the
criticisms going on about
what's exactly the map and the territory
of the fep
I mean the free energy principle because
most people
believe that in fep maps and territories
are conflated
and that's a problematic
a view in so many levels as discussed in
this paper because uh the claim of the
fep uh researchers are not that we uh
have done some conflation of maps and
territories in a uh kind of
as setting on Bayesian mechanics paper a
productive language abuse or notation
abuse way but uh actually these are
exactly uh Maps unto each other and we
cannot separate them
easily and talk about maps and
territories so the the concept of map
Theory
fallacy fallacy comes from this
Viewpoint uh by which this so-called
fallacy is itself another level of
awesome all right on to the next paper
this is going to be a key recent paper
from May 2022 it is on Bayesian
mechanics a physics of and by beliefs
of the beliefs by the beliefs for the
beliefs with ramstead at all
this is active guest stream number 23.1
so on the right here's uh Dalton Maxwell
and Lars and I talking about uh what
looks to be like it's going to be an
American baseball field but actually
it's a path of least action
and this paper
introduces or reintroduces a field of
study that has emerged over the last
decade called Bayesian mechanics and
it's that reintroduction and uh like
nice to meet you again for the first
time which is why Maxwell called The
Stream that we did rebooting the free
energy principle literature
the paper is extremely accessible and
engagingly written it reviews the state
of the art in the literature on the free
energy principle and then in this very
nice figure that we're going to return
to multiple times introduces the three
faces of Bayesian mechanics we're going
to go into them more in the worked
example paper but they are fixed mode
on the left
Dynamic mode
in the middle and then path tracking on
the right side
and the broader or the higher order like
Genera or family level distinction is
the fixed mode seeking and then that
Dynamic mode tracking are regarding
modes of densities Over States whereas
path tracking moves us into a path
native formalism rather than like a
point in state space formalism and
they're all faces of the Bayesian
mechanics under the free energy
principle
and this paper not only discusses those
three faces of Bayesian mechanics but it
examines the duality of the free energy
principle and the constrained maximum
entropy principle
developed and derived and explored in
other Dalton work which we're not going
to talk about here
moving on
that was the key literature
now we're going to stick on this
Bayesian mechanics paper and talk about
three kinds of theories
so the three kinds of theories that
we're going to discuss are dynamics
mechanics and principles and because
Theory can take on many meanings it's
important to quote the authors on how
they use and therefore how we'll try to
use the term so they wrote the word
theory is polysimus it has many meanings
what we have called Dynamics mechanics
and principles are ultimately
mathematical structures in mathematics
these are called mathematical theories
the content of a mathematical Theory or
structure is purely formal
what are usually called scientific
theories or empirical theories comprise
a mathematical structure and what might
be called an empirical application
interpretation or construal of that
system which relates the constructs of
the mathematical structure to things in
the world
so
that is described and explored more in
guest stream 23 and in this paper on
Bayesian mechanics
let's go first two Dynamics
[Music]
um
go for it whoever would like to walk
through these next three
uh well yeah as indicated in amazing
mechanics paper uh we can think about
the Dynamics of a system as a kind of
descriptive or phenomenological
um
let's say description of the system or
uh the uh the kind of description that
uh tries to answer the what questions of
the system so if we look at it uh uh by
the lens of many different uh physics or
mechanics in classical physics we might
uh characterize it as a kind of Galilean
or pre-newtonian Dynamics or in a
statistical physics we can
say the behavioral particles under
diffusion as an example of the Dynamics
of the system in quantum physics we can
talk about the quantum Dynamics as this
kind of phenomenological description
and actually we're talking the other day
about this term Bayesian physics
so we could have used in this slide on
that sure how Dalton would react to that
but in order not to duplicate the other
slide which
talks about Bayesian mechanics
explicitly I've used that term here so
yeah in Bayesian the physics we're
dealing with with the system
the systems by which the Dynamics uh
of a self-organized self-organizing
system or some authors would call Auto
organizing systems
awesome so Dynamics are describing the
what and we're showing Bayesian physics
again with the caveat Ali just mentioned
alongside the three other physics that
we're going to be discussing integration
among
so Dynamics are the what that's how the
Billiards are moving on the table what
is happening
the next level is mechanics so somebody
else may describe mechanics
yes so the mechanics so moving from uh
understanding what the systems uh that
we want to describe are are the Mecha
the mechanics uh can help us answer the
how questions or
actually create the mathematical
formalism that will be able to make
predictions about what is going to
happen and how it happens So In
classical physics we have classical
mechanics either Newtonian lagrangian or
hamiltonian uh in statistical physics we
have statistical mechanics
Quantum quantum mechanics describing how
um
how things behave on a Quantum scale
which we're also going to unpack a bit
further in the coming slides and then
Bayesian mechanics with the mathematical
formalism from the paper physics of
beliefs and also the worked example
um so
the equations that come out of the
mechanics are ones that can be used in a
predictive sense uh all and also in
further trying to understand
um
or in creating new systems that
work on similar principles uh and I
think mentioning principles might uh
continue the good transition into
into the into the third distinction the
why questions
uh which
I can't are kind of these overarching
the uh theorems or rather principles
that
say why things uh
why the what and how questions or topics
work the way they do
um and
principles usually form this kind of
axiomatic uh or take this kind of
axiomatic stance where uh from the
principle everything else uh can be can
be derived or can be put under the
blanket off In classical physics the
principle of stationary action is
definitely one of the most fundamental
that
when when we have uh two points in space
and we want a particle to to
go from one point to another it will
always follow a path of least action a
path of least energy along that path uh
the same uh
the same thing uh is present in
statistical physics and and quantum
physics with quantum physics having the
correspondence principle which is very
relevant in uh in this paper
uh where
the
this in the in the limit of of large of
large numbers Quantum systems
approximate to classical systems uh
which I think
speaks to
uh is also related to the work here in
the in the work example where
um
Quantum systems performing approximate
Bayesian inference in a Quantum setting
um
follow classical paths on average which
will get
into into later and then Bayesian
physics of course having the free
energy principle
awesome
and just to put up what that table looks
like we also had a ton of other
correspondences and rows and columns so
anyone who's interested in this kind of
concordance building work would be
encouraged to participate in the
Institute because this is a really
awesome tool and helps show us
potentially areas where statistical
mechanics has been applied as a
mechanics
can we bring Bayesian mechanics to bear
or areas where stationary action was
applied for classical systems can we
talk about how the free energy principle
might be able to reformulate that or
provide access to new tools or New
Perspectives so this was our uh part of
our table
let's go a little bit deeper into those
three non-bayesian mechanics or the
three non-bayesian physics
again I'm really looking forward to
exploring different ways that we can
think and talk about these different
physics mechanics but just one kind of
way to think about how the special case
of one physics could be an entire other
physics like Jakob just described like
in the so-called classical limit Quantum
systems behave classically but then also
it has a space that goes beyond
classical but that doesn't negate the
relevance or utility or Simplicity of
classical mechanics so how can something
be encompassing but also provide
identity for the special case and it
reminded me of the anatomy of a
mammalian muscle fiber with this kind of
hierarchical organization of blankets it
even looks so much like the blanket
illustrations that we've seen and so we
can think about
um classical
as then being a limit case of
statistical and statistical being a
limit case of quantum and then that is
where Bayesian mechanics is going to
come into play
okay first
classical mechanics who would like to do
their uh short one slider presentation
yes Jacob
um
so
classical mechanics uh as the name
implies uh describes the behavior of
classical objects
um and I think the kind of two main
threats to highlight here that are
relevant even for understanding the
paper uh on the worked example of
Bayesian mechanics is the Newtonian
mechanics which uh
is usually the the
classical mechanics that's uh the first
that people hear about with the with
forces describing how
um uh
with the description of the movements of
objects described how based on how
forces are acting upon them and the
three fundamental laws and then the
lagrangio mechanics which take this more
energy slash
uh principle of least action
um stance where
the main
um
thing of interest is the lagrangian
which is just the kinetic energy minus
the potential energy of the system and
it takes a kind of higher level view of
how uh of given given
um kind of generalized coordinates of
motion how do systems evolve through
time and then of course we could talk
about hamiltonian mechanics which is
just a transformation of lagrangian
mechanics uh but those are the two I
think
main threats to understand and we also
have the principle of uh least
stationary action uh that is described
that can be visualized with uh the
picture in the top right corner
um with the
brickistochrone uh where you have two
points and multiple paths can be
connected to that point but only one
path is the one of least action and in
this case that would be the red path
where if you drop the ball on on that on
that surface uh
the ball following the red curve would
take the least amount of time to travel
between those two points
why is everyone in a hurry
okay
on to statistical mechanics
well here
Ali do you want to go for it
uh well yes uh the
statistical mechanics actually deals
with theories producing the behavior of
systems with probabilistic degrees of
freedom especially the Ensemble level
behavior of large numbers of
functionally identical things at least
according to on Bayesian mechanics paper
but I wanted to point out
a comment made in one of Dalton's posts
about uh the state the status of
statistical mechanics in relation to all
the other areas of physics he writes
beginning from uh Einstein
theoretical physicists
were interested in formulating all these
physical theories in terms of purely
mathematical and rigorous formalisms and
so we have a rigorous theory of
classical mechanics and quantum
mechanics and so on but one conspicuous
absence in this list
is the statistical mechanics here
because or thermodynamics because
although we have some
physicists in the 20th century physicist
mathematicians like James and Carl
McGrath and so on but up to now
statistical physics uh
remains mystery uh not not that all the
related areas of physics for example the
thermodynamical systems condensed matter
and soft matter or biological systems
they remains complete Mysteries so uh
one of Dalton's AIMS in
producing these literature throughout
the past several months uh is at least
to the best of my understanding
is to somehow uh cover up this yawning
Gap in the literature and doing that via
formulating uh this Bayesian mechanics
which can Encompass uh purely
mathematical formalism of statistical
mechanics as well
and uh also
one of the most fundamental principles
of the statistical physics uh which
Dalton has used in these papers in order
to formulate Bayesian mechanics is
James's maximum entropy principle
which is a principle uh by which the
mechanics of statistical objects lead to
diffusion or the descriptive dynamics of
the systems great thank you and from
this paper by about in 2012 we can start
to bridge Quantum and statistical
mechanics by looking at how on different
criteria
they have some concordances so this is
like going one layer deeper into those
concordances
let's go on to Quantum
okay so quantum
we've discussed Quantum a few times on
these live streams
we've discussed some relevant topics in
live stream 17 with Chris fields and
then more recently in live stream number
40 with Fields glaze book glazebrook
friston and Levin
and
would either of you like to describe
Quantum in terms of where it originated
from and how we might be looking at it a
little bit differently here than some
have seen
yeah I uh
I think as uh
physics develop over time and we were
trying to describe uh smaller and
smaller systems that
higher precisions
um at some point we realize that systems
don't obey these uh classical laws set
forth by by Newton or or LaGrange or
others and quantum mechanics is the
formalism for describing systems on a
subatomic scale uh
I think the one of the two major
Concepts
um to mention is the Heisenberg's
uncertainty principle uh which states
that when you have a subatomic particle
you
there's always an uncertainty on its
position in
physical space and its velocity where
there's actually this kind of uh
entanglement of the two in the sense
that if you know one with certainty you
know the other with uncertainty and vice
versa and you have this kind of
um and you can move along this line
where uh
where you can partially know the
position or partially know the velocity
but not both at the same time which I
think is really interesting from the
point of Bayesian mechanics because
quantum mechanics is really the one of
the first
um
subfields of science where the notion of
an observer and the the act of
observation
has needed to be ingrained in the actual
mathematical Theory uh because you can't
just shine a light on an electron
because that will ultimately change the
system uh and so the interaction of the
Observer and and the environment and
Performing inference over uh what what
does uh what do individual how do
individual things in the environment
behave
uh
I think that's something that Bayesian
mechanics is trying to it's trying to
unify and I think the quantum ontology
is very relevant in this case and of
course we
um have
um
there are quantum mechanics is
obviously a large field that's also
um connected to various other fields one
other uh notion to mention would be the
double slit experiment that's depicted
in the in the image on the on the right
which
in it which was one of the first uh if
not the first I'm actually not sure at
the moment uh instances showing the wave
particle duality of subatomic particles
in this case electrons where uh
you just where particles display
behaviors of both waves and
and particles and the behavior is very
dependent on the way that we do our
observations if we want to observe the
electrons passing through a slit before
they reach uh the screen that influences
the behavior the behavior of the
electrons then uh when we look at the
screen after all of the electrons have
passed through the slits
um
so
we have these kind of weak Markov
blankets but without the actual
introduction before the introduction of
weak Markov blankets
awesome it's kind of like all the jokes
around how people behaving differently
when you're observing them
now there's a cognitive analog so some
of those intuitions weren't so far off
after all
and we won't talk about the paper too
much but there's a recent paper from
September 2022 connecting the free
energy principle with Quantum cognition
where they introduce this concept of
excess Bayesian inference which is kind
of like Bayesian inference in a Quantum
lattice it's quite an interesting idea
and it speaks to this intersection of
quantum cognitive theories
not in the sense per se that they've
been developed in the orc or
Quantum microtubule entanglement of
electrons domain which is still like a
physical material
properties topic
thinking about how atomic scale
phenomena have Rippling effects at the
entities level the organism's level
whereas these applications of quantum
cognition to larger cognitive systems
may be absolutely compatible with those
kind of orcor or Quantum microtubule
theories but they do not require that to
happen
it is more going to be referring to
their ability to engage in counter
factual spaces and the relationality
that Jacob mentioned all that brings us
to Bayesian mechanics
okay
who wants to go for basic mechanics
well yeah and Beijing in mechanics we're
dealing with coupled systems that
perform inference over the systems to
which they coupled in other words uh
we're dealing with
particular partitions in this sense of
response 2019 paper or the other uh the
rest of the literature and uh or the
we're looking at the systems that
minimize their own surprisal when the
systems minimize their own surprisal
they must somehow know something about
their environment I mean
inferring something about the external
state is the classical view of the fep
at least as it initially
formulated
but this surprisal minimization follows
from a kind of synchronization between
the the internal and external States
via synchronous synchrony map or Sigma
which is simply the statement the things
which exist reflect the data about their
environments which is their way of
saying the above statement as well
and also
things that are surprising or things
that ought not happen as we expect like
breaking the laws of physics in other
words it might look as a kind of
tautology for a system that would not we
will not expect for a system to behave
in a way in a very surprising way in
other words behave in a way that obey
obey the laws of physics but one of the
main points of the Bayesian mechanics is
to formulate this exact Viewpoint by not
focusing on a single trajectory of a
behavior but by somehow
generalizing that statement to a whole
fiber bundles of behavior as they say in
the gauge Theory so uh and uh systems in
this
sense
can somehow be duly described uh instead
of the traditional view of the fep uh
they can be described from the other way
around by using the constraints maximum
entropy principle I mean instead of
looking at the system or agent from the
inside and trying to trying to somehow
formulate uh its inference of the of its
external Behavior external State we can
put the observer in the external
environment looking at the system and
deriving the exact same formula
formulation by just flipping around or
inverting the sigma synchrony map
so that's one of the I believe Central
ideas uh of sorry Central ideas of
Bayesian mechanics
Jacob
I would uh
just kind of summarize that by pointing
attention to uh the image in on the
slide
um
already caption I'll read the caption
and you can provide an image meme
analysis the left side says when the
tree blows and shakes a tree branch it
is because the tree branch has inertia
but not enough to resist the force of a
wind
on another Dot and then on the right
side
it says when the wind blows and shakes a
tree branch it is because the tree
branch reduces its surprisal about the
state of the World by modeling it
yes so these are essentially equivalent
statements one from the classical
perspective another from the Bayesian
mechanical perspective uh
I think this notion might initially
sound counter-intuitive uh which is why
I think it's good to
um
start talking about it now so that it uh
has time to to settle by by the time we
reach G Theory
um
I think
that pretty much summarizes it
yes it's
pan inferentialist
without being pan psychist per se
Ali also pointed to that extremely
important theoretical duel between the
free energy principle and constrained
maximum entropy principle which then was
mapped onto this View From the Inside
which is kind of a strategic agent
trying to synchronize with external
States or learn or reduce their surprise
about external States as mediated by the
blanket States that's the view from the
inside and the view from the outside
which brings us to the relationality
Jacob raised in the quantum space
the view from the outside is as an
experimenter and the fact that Dalton
has shown that these two Frameworks are
dual to each other is provided some of
the most important theoretical synthesis
in the area
now the three phases of Bayesian
mechanics so I'll uh bring larger a
slide that was shared at iy recently the
2022 conference
and it shows the three faces of Bayesian
mechanics mode matching mode tracking
path tracking those are the three phases
that also are reflected in the earlier
paper and that was guest stream 23.1
in addition here we see on the right is
this chaos and that is kind of um a
little bit beyond where we're going to
go today but it's an exciting Direction
so does anyone want to describe the
three faces and then we'll head into the
topics and paper
um
do you think
maybe because we uh have like detailed
um size for each of the
yeah just to say that these are three
different faces of basic mechanics and
we'll talk more about them soon okay
here are some topics we're not going to
talk about them at all at all but we
left some open slides and space to add
even more because they're topics that we
want to talk with Dalton and you all
about
so supersymmetry this was the citation
in the paper
free energy principle and constrained
maximum entropy Principle as theoretical
duels
Bayesian fermions bosons and ghost
fields
and anything else that people bring up
we made it to the paper
let's review the road map before we
really head off on this journey
and to make this a reasonable dot zero
and not go out too far beyond what we
all understand here
we're just going to be really looking at
a few
uh key points
and if either of you want to highlight
something please just raise your hand
and highlight it on that slide otherwise
we're just going to take a brief stroll
through the paper
so again just raise your hand on the
slide if you want to say something
the paper begins with a formalization
um or a a scoping of the formalizations
that will come
in terms of Bayesian mechanics and about
how it's going to connect to derivations
of classical physics constrained maximum
entropy or constrained maximum caliber
as well as supersymmetry theory in
classical mechanics
section 2 classical physics in one
dimension
is studying the mechanics of classical
objects and the way in which that they
embody Newton's Law
which is that systems accelerate along
Force gradients
think back to jakob's distinction
between Newtonian mechanics as forces
acting on objects versus the lagrangian
formalization
precisely in the direction and magnitude
of the total Force applied no more and
no less
section 2A continues Along on this
direction
and talks about different ways that
mechanics can be specified around Motion
in gravitational fields like moving
objects and also approximations arising
from fluid flow
section 2B is the basics of Bayesian
mechanics
Bayesian mechanics can be seen as an
account of the laws of motion deriving
from the fep
concerning how Bayesian beliefs
that is systems with beliefs such as
coupled random dynamical systems which
perform inference over the things to
which they couple
behave under certain determinants of
probabilistic motion
and this is another really interesting
note much like classical mechanics
serves as an account of systems that
obey Newton's second law by minimizing
classical action
Bayesian mechanics is an account of
systems that engage in approximate
Bayesian inference by minimizing
surprisal
so the ball minimizes energy by Falling
the candle minimizes Gibbs free energy
by burning
cognitive systems are minimizing free
energy by way of minimizing surprisal
otherwise they would fail to be that
thing
2B
continues on
to to be or not to be
the pure physics of the fep arguably
dates back to two Landmark papers in the
literature
a free energy principle for particular
physics first in 2019 and Mark out
blankets information geometry and
stochastic thermodynamics which we
didn't review here
the fep has gestured at a new sort of
physics
and that is what this work is recently
bringing a
quite exciting Crescendo and examples of
and here is a referral to the Dual
nature of fep and constrained maximum
entropy
continuing on in section 2B
we see a little bit of an unpacking
around the idea that the fep is a least
action principle a pride to surprisal
where the application of least surprisal
principle to specific objects determines
mathematical or determines the
mechanical theory about these objects
so
would be awesome for those who are
familiar with Edo calculus and
stochastic differential equations
lagrangian mechanics and path
probability measures
here we get to equation 15 Ali if you
want to unpack a little bit What's
Happening Here
is actually equation 15 is the kind of
generalization
of equation five for a modal path given
by the equation 12
and this equation
is described as the general equation for
Bayesian classical mechanics or we can
see that as the most Central equation by
which all the other results or their
derivations can potentially be derived I
guess
so here Q
represents the position but as a slight
caveat here uh because in most other
literature Q is used for uh the uh for
designating the recognition density but
in this paper recognition density is
designated with r so the Q is reserved
for position
and obviously T is also the time uh the
lambdas here represents the the LaGrange
multipliers
uh and we have uh kind of limiting uh
a limiting situation or limiting
condition in which uh the inverse of
Lambda is much lower than one and the
Lambda 2 is equals to one yes that's
exactly
the points there and in this limiting
situation we can reproduce the classical
Dynamics in particular in the limit
Lambda 1 uh
it goes to Infinity there is no
uncertainty at all and the most likely
path under those constraints the
classical path of least action by
construction is the only path we land
any non-zero probability to so all the
other uh classical and even Quantum
derivations can potentially be uh again
be derived from this Central equation
here
great we have all the equations prepared
to explore further now we're going to go
into those three faces of Bayesian
mechanics so
let's just start with mode matching
Jacob do you want to describe mode
matching
yeah so mode matching uh is the simplest
case of Bayesian Mechanics for
stationary objects
um the interesting thing that uh Delta
mentioned in the paper is that mode
matching is only really valid for brief
time scales implying that nothing ever
really stays stationary uh
I would be interested to
uh unpack this further in the dot one
and the dot two how brief these time
scales can uh can actually be is it just
instantaneous is anything ever
stationary and how are different
reference frames involved but in the
simplest case uh we can
uh mode matching considers objects that
at least uh in the approximate sense are
stationary like a ball uh resting on the
ground where the ball
is essentially doing approximate
Bayesian inference on the on its
gravitational pull and on the normal
force that is uh acting to resist that
gravitational pull and in the Bayesian
mechanical sense if it wouldn't do that
that would be surprising and therefore
it wouldn't be a ball because it would
fail to
act within the confines of the
environment and
therefore in mode matching
um Bayesian mechanics
does reduce to or rather imply Newton's
first law where for every uh for every
applied force there is a force of equal
magnitude applied in the opposite
direction or for every action there's a
reaction
great like why don't you ever change
your mind
I'm mode matching what are you talking
about
I'm doing optimal Bayesian inference
I've been doing it all day
okay
mode tracking so in mode tracking
we're going to now generalize from that
ball resting on the ground to what
setting Ali or Jacob
uh well yeah in the mode tracking unlike
the case of mood matching we have uh
the target mode or the desired mode
um toward which the systems
um are tracking so that's uh I believe
the the main difference between the mode
matching and the mill tracking
approaches uh so uh but uh within the
mode tracking we also have two subtypes
of mode tracking one of which is the
terminal mode matching and the other one
is the infinite mode tracking
so in the case of terminal mode matching
we already have the
terminal modes toward which the system
and actually somehow uh the
probabilistic states the probabilistic
space of the system uh tracks its
trajectory but in the case of infinite
mode tracking uh we don't have a I mean
some end points because it's a kind of
uh analogous to a circular satellite
motion uh by which we don't have the
beginning and the end of the trajectory
so uh also this kind of mode tracking uh
has been described as a as an
alternative term a mode chasing
uh so I believe uh we can
elaborate and unpack the details of that
with tolton
great Jacob
I will just add to the infinite modes
tracking case one very interesting
um
um thing that Dalton mentioned in the
paper is that when you have this when
you have a constant path That's
essential uh that you're performing the
infinite mode tracking on the the state
uh of the the surprisal of your states
are always
non-zero which
I find really interesting because uh for
me it kind of implies that there's
always a certain level of uncertainty
but at the same time this contrasts with
the infinite case where for for the case
of planets orbiting orbiting the Sun
um
the there's there shouldn't be that much
uncertainty about about the path because
you know you're going to follow that
path uh
for uh till the end of time uh just
one thing that I found interesting
awesome so again just to recap for those
who are looking for those worked
examples
in the mode matching case we have a ball
on the ground
the mass is not moving
we then have a situation where the
equilibrium steady state so to say
is not
where the mass is now the center of
gravity is in motion in the mode
matching case the center of gravity is
not in motion
the two cases of mode tracking where the
center of gravity needs to be moving
cognitive center of gravity is terminal
mode matching which is equivalent to a
ball thrown in a parabola where there
are some defined endpoints but it's
moving along a path of least action
towards that endpoint
and infinite mode tracking where it's in
a continuous dynamical or oscillatory
acceleration process and again it's
super interesting to think about what
these actually entail cognitively
I'm sure we'll get there
on to section seven so section seven
broadens the discussion from the state
tracking uh framework of modes
remembering this
image
where all of the modes whether fixed
mode or dynamic mode are regarding
densities Over States now we have
densities over paths enabled by the
gauge theoretic formalisms so
here are some equations and quotes
related to path tracking anything to add
foreign
yes go ahead go ahead yeah
sorry I was just explicitly mention uh
one point on the slide that the
formulation that path tracking is
essentially the formulation of mode
tracking seen as a gradient Ascent on
the path probability density I think
that
um is
um
an important notion uh in under in
understanding what the difference
between path tracking and most tracking
is
um and also uh
maybe uh as a slight
mathematical joke uh the usage of of the
word reduces to when moving in between
equations that employ the path tracking
uh formalism uh
can also be a bit uncertain on the on
the first on the first read
Holly
okay
yes I also wanted to mention that
active inference is kind of uh subsumed
in this type of path tracking systems so
and also the initial formulations of fep
up to 2019 uh I mean especially the 2019
car for instance uh monograph
implicitly deals with this path tracking
approach as far as I know but somehow
this typology of different kind of
Bayesian mechanics is
a pretty new to these uh recent
literature and uh before that uh there
was a lot of there were a lot of
confusions and misunderstanding about
what kind of systems are we dealing with
uh in each
paper
awesome
then at the very end
there's a first idea of G Theory
so just like variational free energy has
F equation 2.5 from the textbook and
expected free energy is G equation 2.6
in the textbook here we move from F free
energy principle Tristan
to G
Beyond
and we'll talk more about this with
Dalton
but
if anybody wants to add anything they're
welcome to
I think uh one uh one thread that was
open towards the end of the paper was
with the application of G Theory to uh
to uh chaos with the notion that
we can use Bayesian mechanics to stud to
study systems that uh
that uh seem that are dependent on the
initial the initial conditions and even
though this uh this was so far purely
described in the context of
non-biological entities I think it's
really exciting to see the potential
applications in applied active inference
where the your initial belief states do
influence your trajectory through uh
through the through the uh the high
dimensional State space and
I think it will be very interesting to
see how G Theory develops in that way
and to see more
connections between how we can use
um Notions from supersymmetry and chaos
to studying cognitive systems or
physical systems cognitively
uh
yeah awesome very well said like there
are phase transitions or critical
moments where when the ball falls on one
side of the roof it goes that way and
when it falls on the other side of the
roof it goes a different way
and there are just noticeable
differences in terms of our
psychophysics
and this is really bringing the physics
to psychophysics and
it's been quite a journey
if either of you have any
penultimate thoughts please provide them
well as I said before
um it's been an extremely fascinating
learning experience for me personally
and I'm very much looking forward to
discuss all of these uh stunning ideas
with Dalton and learn much more so
thanks to everyone
thank you Ali Jacob
yeah I think I
made my own over uh
um my kind of ending remark uh with the
with the last uh comment but yeah it's
been it's been an incredible journey so
far and definitely and an extremely fun
experience to try to unpack this and uh
in in our discussions and I look forward
to unpacking even more and uh
seeing how how uh This Thread develops
yes thanks both and Andre for all the
work leading up to it and until next
time
thanks bye